Hello all, today we are going to look at
what MCP, Model Context Protocol, actually
is.
We all know MCP is a way of connecting our
data and tools to AI applications.
But if we were asked what MCP exactly is
or why it is a must for AI application
these days or how it is helping engineers
and product owners to simplify the
connection, not many of us can answer the
question clearly, right?
In this video, I will use one simple
example the whole way through, like a
support agent for an online store and we
will look at it from architecture's point
of view step-by-step.
In this video, we are going to run through
five different topics.
Number one, how AI agents are built before
MCP even existed.
And number two, what are all the
drawbacks?
What are all the disadvantages we had with
that approach?
And number three, what MCP is?
Why MCP came into existence?
And number four, what are all the
different benefits we get out of it?
And finally, we will look at why the name
Model Context Protocol, we will go through
word by word and understand what each term
within the name Model Context Protocol is.
So before we go in detail about it, we
need to understand an example.
So let's say you are a backend engineer of
a company which owns Amazon-like
e-commerce website.
And let's say the website has project
management API, order management API,
payment and refund API, or notification
API, which is serving your website, okay?
And the users are demanding you to create
an AI agent which can answer questions for
this website.
And that is our example.
So we are going to build this agent
together, and we are going to build it
without MCP in it.
So how the agents look like?
So usually the agent looks like with two
main components.
One is support agent, which is like the
actual code of the agent.
And the LLM can be chat GPT or Gemini, or
any large language model.
So the user asked the question in, and it
goes to support agent, and the support
agent asks LLM, and LLM gives with a
user-friendly answer, and that is written
to the user.
So in this case, if the user is asking
like, where is my order?
It goes to LLM.
And in this case, it doesn't have that
kind of knowledge, because order has to
come from order management API, and it is
not attached.
So it doesn't have that information to
return back.
So as engineer, now you're going to add
order management API capability to your
support agent.
And what you're doing, you are integrating
the order management API to your agent.
And you're adding the instruction to your
LLM on how to use it, when to use it, and
what input to send.
And also, you're updating the support
agent to how to request this API, and make
a call to this API, and get the response
back.
So let's say you have set that up.
And now the user is asking, where is my
order now?
So what is going to happen is more like
the agent is going to ask the LLM, what
should I do?
And the LLM has all the instruction now.
So the moment it receives a question like,
where is my order?
The instruction to LLM says like, you need
to call order management API.
So LLM is going to send the response back
to the agent saying that call order
management API, and pause this already.
Now agent calls the order management API
directly.
And API returns the raw order data.
Agent extracts the status status, and
sends it to LLM.
And LLM responds to the user saying your
order is being packed for delivery.
So this is how the flow looks like for one
question.
So now the user is impressed.
And user asks another question, can I find
a product in blue color?
And now again, the agent is going to ask
LLM now, I received a question like, can I
find the product in blue color?
And what should I do?
And the instruction doesn't say anything
about the product details.
All it has is all the instructions about
the order details.
But this is about the product and no
details available.
So in this case, the LLM is going to
return saying, sorry, I'm unable to answer
the question.
So how do you improve your support agent?
You can improve your support agent by
adding the project management API.
So you have gone through the same process.
Now you have updated the instruction to
include details for product management API
as well.
So the LLM has all the information of both
APIs available for it to call and receive
answers.
And you also upgraded your support agent
so that it can call order management API
or product management API when it is
required.
Now the user asked the question, can I get
this in blue?
And again, the question is sent from agent
to LLM and LLM response saying it follows
the instruction and it says like, OK, now
you need to call project management API
and pass the color as blue.
So agents builds their JSON request and
calls the product management API.
API returns the raw data and this is
extracted and sent to LLM and LLM puts in
a nice friendly response to the user.
So now your support agent can answer
questions on orders and it can also answer
questions on products.
All right, good.
So next, the user wanted to know if he can
get a refund for his product.
So in this case, a refund means you need
to have access to payment and refund API,
which is not there.
So unfortunately, at this time, the LLM is
going to respond saying sorry, I'm unable
to answer the question.
So again, the engineer had to go through
another upgrade to your support agent.
So now he's adding one more payment and
refund API to it, updating the
instructions to the LLM and
updating the support agent to integrate
this new payment and refund API.
So this is a working example and we know
this is going to work and this is how
exactly it was working before AMCP comes
into existence.
When it all works, what is the problem?
The problem is it doesn't scale well.
There are three major drawbacks that shows
as soon as we have gone through second
version or third version or including
second API or third API to the agent.
And what are those drawbacks?
The first drawback is the APIs are tightly
coupled now to the agent, which means
every time you upgrade the agent, you're
adding more code base to the agent.
So which means when the support agent was
V1, it was tightly coupled to order API.
And when the support agent upgraded to V2,
it has details of both order API and
product API and V3, it has details of
order API, product API and payment API,
and it is all tightly coupled.
So in case if you wanted to remove the
support agent and add another financial
agent, you have to do everything from the
scratch, nothing you can reuse it, right?
And the second drawback is it contains
APIs are low level details.
So every time you wanted to integrate an
API into your agent, you need to give
instructions about inputs and output
schemas, passing, error handling, retries,
and you need to literally do all the
plumbing work within the support agent.
Technically, the support agent should be
as simple as making a call and getting the
response.
But unfortunately, here we are directly
integrating the API, which means all the
plumbing goes into the support agent.
And the third drawback is it makes the
agent more and more complex every time.
So the first version was easy.
But the second version has two API
integrations, which mean it was moderately
complex.
And the third version, it got difficult
because it is integrating three different
API's, which means it has all the details
of three different API's now.
And there is no ceiling for this, the more
API's you add, the more data source you
add, it's going to get more and more
complicated.
So that's where the MCP comes into
picture.
So what is MCP?
Let's quickly go through what MCP is.
And we will try to build the same support
agent using MCP now.
So MCP in very simple terms, it is a
common communication language that is
built between I mean, it is used between
LLM powered application, and the tools we
want them to use to answer questions.
So it's as simple as you have LLM powered
apps on one side, and tools on the other
side, and you're going to use this MCP to
communicate between those two different
components.
We are taking the same example again,
again, you have this user and you have the
support agent.
And this time, the support agent, it is
going to make call to ecommerce MCP
server.
So instead of it directly integrating to
the API, it is going to make call to the
ecommerce MCP server, and it is going to
get the details black.
So this is more like a client server
architecture, which means you will have
MCP client sitting attached to the support
agent, and MCP client is going to call the
ecommerce server.
And ecommerce server has all different set
of tools.
And how this
architecture works, so whenever the
support agent is initiated or initialized,
the MCP client discovers the menu of
tools, it is going to make a quick call to
know all the tools that is available
within the MCP service.
So in this example, it has get orders,
order details, order status, get products,
product details, etc.
And the ecommerce MCP server is going to
have the instruction, the details on what
each tool does.
So the support agent doesn't have anything
when it is initialized.
And the moment the ecommerce MCP server is
attached to it, it made a call, it asked
to return the list of tools, and it also
comes with the instruction.
So by the time the support agent read all
the tools available, it also knows where
in which case which tool to use.
So let's take this example.
So where is my order now?
So when the user asks, where is my order
now, now, first, when the agent is
initialized, it is asking like, give me
all your tools, and by the time it has got
all the details of the tools, and also the
instructions on when to use each tool.
So now when the question is asked, the
agent knows it pick it has to pick order
details and calls it the server
replacement order status already in the
form of LLM that it can read.
So whatever outcome, whatever output that
MCP server produces, it is in the same
format which the LLM can easily understand
and directly post it to the user, it
doesn't have to go through a JSON format
and message or good bunch of details that
it has to filter out to find the detail it
already has all the information in a
simple text format that it can take it
from the ecommerce MCP server and directly
post it to the user.
And one more big advantage is you don't
have to build the MCP server on your own
every time.
So for example, in our case, we had four
different API's product management API,
order management API, and payment and
refund API, and notification API, let's
say.
So let's say you're using a tool called
Stripe for payment and refunds, and Slack
for messaging and notification, these are
well known products for payment refunds
and messaging and notification right.
So most probably they have their own
official MCP server published for their
products.
So on that case, your support agent can be
as simple as you're creating your own
company or the MCP server, only to get
product and orders details.
But to do the payment and refunds, you can
use Stripe MCP and for messaging and
notification, you can use Slack MCP.
And these days, each and every major
software company, they are coming up with
their own set of MCP servers, which you
can directly use it within your system.
Why is this worth?
What are all the benefits that this is
bringing?
So what are all the advantages you get by
using MCP server instead of you directly
integrating one of the API to your ISE
agent?
The first one is reusability.
So in our example, so far, what we have
done is we have the support agent, which
is making a call to ecommerce MCP server
to get the details back.
So you have a dedicated ecommerce MCP
server, and this can not only be used by
support agent, but it can also be used by
different agents in the future.
For example, in the future, if you have
finance agent that it needs to use the
ecommerce MCP server, it just it is as
simple as just plug and play.
And the future, if you're going to add one
more executive or manager agent, and if it
requires order details or product details,
it is as simple as plug and play.
You don't have to make any changes.
All you have to do is to do the
configuration to call this MCP server by
using the URL HTTPS ecommerce site.com
slash MCP.
And that's it.
You have it there.
So many agents can use the same ecommerce
MCP server.
The next one is it is loosely coupled.
So in this example, we have this ecommerce
MCP server.
Just in case in the future, if you have
another competitive ecommerce MCP server
ecommerce product that you wanted to use,
you can easily swap it, just switch it.
So in this example, as you can see here,
it has moved to Amazon ecommerce MCP
server.
So previously, it was like the company
owned one, and you can easily switch it to
other ecommerce server.
So there is no like hardwired connection
between the agents and MCP servers.
It is loosely coupled, and it gives
immense advantage for anybody doing
enterprise architecture.
And the third advantage is the
scalability.
So you got like five different tools
within your MCP servers in the future, if
you want to add more tools like
introducing update product, which will
update the product or introducing delete
product, which will delete the product.
You can just simply upgrade the MCP
servers, and the rules and regulations are
automatically populated and it is ready to
use on all the agents now.
So you don't have to do the code changes
on any of the support agents or finance
agents.
That is all completely fixed.
All you have to do is upgrade your MCP
server and deploy it, and it is all
readily available to be used, the new
tools also are readily available to be
used by support agent, finance agent or
manager agents for that.
So these are all massive, massive, big
advantages that MCP server brings in when
it is used with our support agent.
Why the name model context protocol?
Three words, and definitely each one has
its own meaning that makes the term model
context protocol.
First, we will see what is protocol?
Protocol is nothing but a shared set of
rules for correct communication.
A protocol is a set of rules and standard
procedures that guides correct behavior or
technical
communication, for example, HTTP.
So HTTP is widely used protocol between
the web client and the web server.
So web clients, if you have a web server
like google.com, and if it has used HTTP
protocol to expose the screen in HTML
format, then Chrome can access it, Firefox
can access it, Edge can access it.
You don't have to do a separate code for
your web application to run in Chrome
browser or Firefox browser, right?
That's what the protocols advantages.
It follows the same set of rules that is
applicable for any browser, and you
develop one application and one web
application, and that is readily
accessible by any browsers.
Similarly, MCP is another protocol.
So it comes with set of rules or standard
procedures that anybody wanted to do it so
that the
communication is stable, and you can use
it between any AI models and MCP server
tools.
That's protocol for us.
And what is model?
So the word model, model context protocol,
built specifically means this MCP is built
specifically for AI models.
So AI models like GPT, Gemini, or cloud
powered app.
So model is designed for AI models, and it
is not for web applications or mobile
apps.
APIs are written for human written code to
request and retrieve JSON with MCP.
The LLM itself first discovers all the
available tools, understand the
capabilities, and decide which one to use.
So that's where the model comes into
picture.
And finally, what is context?
It's more like memory across multiple
steps.
So if you notice when you're using chat
GPT, or any agent for that matter, you can
say I want to refund it, that it is the
order the user asked about 30 seconds ago.
But when in this sentence, it doesn't have
any value, but just because it has a
memory, and it can remember what is the
discussion about and which order is
currently being discussed now, when the
user says I want to refund it, it knows
the it in the sentence, it means the order
which is currently in discussion.
So to put it simply, LLM powered app, it
contains its own LLM.
And it has its MCP client, which is used
to connect to MCP servers.
And the context storage, it's a memory
that holds the tools details, and the
instructions of when the tools to use, and
it has a memory to remember some of the
history.
So that's why the context comes into
picture.
And it is called model context protocol.
So to put it simply, MCP is a protocol
designed specifically for AI models.
And it maintains context across multi step
interaction within tools.
So there is one topic or one method that
comes into play every time is MCP
replacement for the API.
No, it is not MCP is not a replacement for
the API.
MCP gives AI models and applications a
common interface, and a simplified LLM
friendly response.
But it sits on top of the API, it doesn't
replace it, API is used by human written
code to make a call and get the response
back.
But the MCP is more like it will, it is a
communication protocol between the AI
model and the MCP server.
So in this example, as you can see, MCP
server looks more LLM friendly, like it
will have the content type equals text,
and text is your orders being packed for
delivery.
But if it is a raw API response, it will
be more like already order name, date of
order, status, etc, etc.
So MCP is definitely not a replacement of
API API will be still used across multiple
web services and websites to make a call
and get the data back.
But MCP comes into play when you're doing
ai agent or ai application that needs access
to the data sources, which is available
via MCP.
I hope that gives you a quick overview of
how MCP comes into picture and plays an
important role between connecting AI
agents with other data and tools.
And the next video, we will try to do a
hands on coding session where we will
create ai agent and create an MCP server
and we will try to connect this MCP server
into our agent and give it a try.
Until then, thank you very much for
watching and I'll see you in the next
video.